Finding Aid for Robert M. Warner Papers, 1945-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- National Archives
  - NARS Independence
    - Congressional Publications
      - Congressional Reports on H.R. 3987 & S. 905 (Box 12)
  - Preservation
    The National Archives' efforts to improve its preservation program are documented in the subseries Preservation. Miscellaneous materials from 1982, 1983 and 1985 pertaining to this topic comprise one folder. Another folder contains materials relating to the Committee on Preservation. The work of this committee culminated in 1984 in a twenty-year preservation plan, constituting a third folder.
    - Miscellaneous 1982-1983, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Committee on Preservation (Box 12)
    - Twenty-year Preservation Plan 1984 (Box 12)
  - Presidential Libraries
    The Presidential Libraries subseries contains materials relating to the Richard Nixon papers and library, and the Gerald Ford, Jimmy Carter and Ronald Reagan presidential libraries. Within each file, records are arranged chronologically. During Warner's years as Archivist, the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library was established, while plans were underway for the Carter Library and discussions were just beginning on the Reagan library.
    Three folders contain Nixon materials, including those pertaining to the Nixon Presidential Materials Project. This project related to the then-recently passed Presidential Records Act, which stipulated that the papers of any President of the United States were federal property. The materials in these folders document the National Archives' efforts to gain custody of the Nixon papers. Included also are statements regarding presidential libraries which Warner made before two federal committees. A miscellaneous folder holds related materials covering the years 1983 and 1984, as well as a few undated items.
    - Nixon Papers 1980 (Box 12)
    - Nixon Papers January 1981 (Box 12)
    - Nixon Papers 1983, undated (Box 12)
    - Ford Presidential Library (Box 12)
    - Carter Presidential Library (Box 12)
    - Reagan Presidential Library (Box 12)
    - Statement before Subcommittee on Government Information, Justice and Agriculture of the Committee on Government Operations 1985 (Box 12)
    - Testimony on S. 1325 re: Presidential Libraries (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous 1983-1984 (Box 12)
  - FBI Records
    The FBI Records subseries contains materials documenting NARS action in 1980 and 1981 regarding the appraisal and retention of the Federal Bureau of Investigation's records. A two-volume report to the district court judge for the District of Columbia on the appraisal of these papers is included.
    - NARS Action 1980-1981 (Box 13)
    - Appraisal of the Records of the Federal Bureau of Investigation: A Report to Hon. Harold H. Greene, United District Court for the District of Columbia November 9, 1981, 2 volumes (Box 13)
  - Task Forces
    Task Forces materials are arranged topically and include reports and correspondence. The Prologue Task Force contains materials relating to the evaluation of Prologue, the journal published by the National Archives. Especially significant are two folders of materials documenting the activities of the Smithsonian Institution Task Force.
    - Adequacy of Documentation Task Force 1982 (Box 13)
    - Appraisal and Disposition Task Force (Box 13)
    - National Information Systems Task Force (Box 13)
    - Prologue Task Force (Box 13)
    - Records Declassification Task Force 1983 (Box 13)
    - Smithsonian Institution Task Force, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Topical Files A-Z
    The Topical Files subseries contains materials arranged alphabetically by topic. Included are files concerning the Central Intelligence Agency's (CIA) report to the committees of Congress on the declassification of records and to the Archives' program on exhibits. The Archival Fairytales folder contains an unidentified creator's lighthearted look at archives legislation dating from 1981 and 1982. An interviewing file includes a GSA checklist of questions to ask personnel. Three folders contain papers related to appointments of personnel, including the Deputy Archivist of the United States. The professional development efforts file relates to discussion surrounding the need for the development of policies regarding GSA and NARA employees' outside publishing interests. Materials pertaining to the proposed renovation of the National Archives building comprise an additional folder.
    - 50th Anniversary Plans (Box 13)
    - Annual Report 1982 (Box 13)
    - Budget Info 1980-1985 (Box 13)
    - Central Intelligence Agency (Box 13)
    - Electronic and Machine Readable Records (Box 13)
    - Exhibits (Box 13)
    - Fairytales (Box 13)
    - Independence (letters of support, copies of congressional bills, notes) (Box 13)
    - Information Institute 1985 (Box 13)
    - Information Technology (Box 13)
    - Introduction to NARS 1985 (Box 13)
    - Kahlil Gibran Centennial (Box 13)
    - Legal Issues (Box 13)
    - Management (including GSA's Management Monthly mailing) (Box 13)
    - Management Plan for 1984-1989 (Box 13)
    - Misc. Business Records (Box 13)
    - Modern Archives Institute (Box 13)
    - National Historic Publications and Records Commission (NHPRC) (Box 13)
    - NARS Planning Council (Box 13)
    - NARS New Building Planning (Box 13)
    - Oral History (Box 13)
    - Personnel Appointments, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Professional Development (Box 13)
    - Program Briefings/Current Issues 1981 March (Box 13)
    - Program Briefings/Current Issues 1984 October (Box 14)
    - Program Review 1980 (Box 14)
    - Records and Information Management (Box 14)
    - Renovations (Box 14)
    - Technology Assessment (Box 14)
    - Trust Fund (Box 14)
    - Acceptance Address Outline 1980 (Box 14)
    - Performance Appraisal Materials (Box 14)
    - Resignation and Departure of Robert M. Warner October 1984-April 1985 (Box 14)
    - Farewell Letters from Washington Colleagues (Box 14)
    - Farewell Letters from the National Historical Publications and Records Commission (Box 14)
    - Newsletters, July / August 1980 December 1984 April 1985 (Box 14)
    - Papers on Electronic and Machine-Readable Records (Box 14)
  - Post-National Archives
    The Post-National Archives materials are divided into two topical files, arranged chronologically. The first, dating from June 1985 to November 1987, consists of correspondence and article clippings on the process of appointing Warner's successor as Archivist of the United States. This material is significant for the insight it gives into the issue of the politicization of the position of Archivist of the U.S. Much of the material relates to the campaign to prevent John Agresto, the candidate first selected by President Reagan, from being appointed. The second topical file contains papers relating to the appointment of Don Wilson as seventh Archivist of the United States. Particularly noteworthy are Warner's remarks, which he delivered at the swearing-in of Wilson.
    - Appointment of Archivist of U.S. June 1985-November 1987 (Box 14)
    - Don Wilson, 7th Archivist of U.S. December 1987-February 1989 (Box 14)
    - National Archives and Records Administration 1986 Congressional (Box 14)
  - Budget Hearings Binder (Box 14)
- School of Information and Library Studies 1985-1997
  The School of Information and Library Studies (SILS) series (5 linear feet) documents Warner's time a Dean of SILS and interim head of the library system at the University of Michigan's from 1985 to 1992. The SILS Dean's Files subseries includes correspondence, travel records, speeches, meetings and conferences, and materials relating to curriculum development, courses taught, archives courses development, faculty meetings, faculty search committees, and fundraising. This series also includes the ALA and SAA chapters at the University of Michigan, the Ford Motor Company history project, the History and Traditions Committee, and numerous library committees and symposiums.
  - Dean's Files
    - Archives Program Curriculum Proposal (Box 15)
    - Archives Course Preparatory Materials (Box 15)
    - Atkins (Daniel) (Box 15)
    - Associations and Affiliations, 38 folders (Box 15)
    - Beth Yakel (Box 38)
      [SR RESTRICTED until 2075 ]
    - Celebration '87, 6 folders (Box 15)
    - Consulting (National Institute of Standards and Technology) 1991 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence as Dean (Box 15)
    - Correspondence 1985-1988, 5 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1989-1992, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence 1993-1997, 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence (arranged alphabetically)
      - Bidlack, Russell (Box 16)
      - Boaz, Martha (Box 16)
      - Church, Michael (Box 16)
      - Dougherty, Richard (Box 16)
      - Fine (Sidney) Retirement (Box 16)
      - Frye, Billy (Box 16)
      - Hanke, Lewis (Box 16)
      - Mellon Foundation (Box 16)
      - National Archives and Records Administration (Box 16)
      - National Association of Government Archives and Records Administrators (NAGARA) (Box 16)
      - Presidents (letters of) (Box 16)
      - Rosenthal, Samuel (Box 16)
      - Shapiro, Harold (Box 16)
      - Van Houweling, Douglas (Box 16)
    - Course Evaluations 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Curriculum (Box 16)
    - Dean's Summary 1992 (Box 16)
    - Development (Box 16)
    - Faculty Meetings (Box 16)
    - Faculty Retreat 1993 (Box 16)
    - Faculty Search Committee (Box 16)
    - Fundraising (Box 16)
    - General Correspondence 1993 (Box 16)
    - Independent Study & Field Experience (Box 16)
    - M-Campaign (Box 16)
    - Office Correspondence Records 1992 (Box 16)
    - Meetings and Conferences, 9 folders (Box 17)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Preservation Grant 1986 (Box 17)
    - Ph.D. Students-Anne Gilliland-Swetland (Box 17)
    - Phone Calls (Box 17)
    - Seminar Materials (Box 17)
    - Speeches and Talks (Box 17)
    - Tate Chair (Box 17)
    - Jones, Thomas L. (Box 17)
    - Travel, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Vance Fund (Box 17)
  - ALA-SAA Joint Committee
    - 1988-1989 (Box 17)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 17)
    - ALA Conference January 1992 (Box 17)
    - ALA Conference June 1992 (Box 17)
  - Clements Library (Box 17)
  - Expanded Parking Paradigm (Box 17)
  - Ford Motor Company History Project
    - Advisory Committee (Box 17)
    - Drafts (Box 17)
  - History and Traditions Committee
    - Agendas (Box 18)
    - Architecture (Box 18)
    - Biannual Reports (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Detroit Observatory (Box 18)
    - Minutes (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
    - Projects (Box 18)
    - Related Materials (Box 18)
    - Steneck, Nick and Margaret (Box 18)
    - Task Lists 1991-1992, 1995, 4 folders (Box 18)
  - Information Symposium 1990-1991 (Box 19)
  - Recommendation letters (Box 38)
    [SR RESTRICTED until 2070 ]
  - Robert Warner Symposium October, 1996 (Box 19)
  - Schlessinger Library Visiting Committee (Box 19)
  - Smithsonian Symposium (Box 19)
  - State of the Library Speech 1989-1990 (Box 19)
  - University Library (Box 19)
  - University Library Management Review Committee (Box 19)
- Teaching Materials and Scholarly Research
  Teaching Materials and Scholarly Research series (2.5 linear feet) contains Warner's lecture notes for his University of Michigan history and archives courses along with copies of his thesis, drafts and final versions of articles submitted for publication, and early drafts of Diary of a Dream. Also included are documents from his time teaching at UCLA (1992) such as lecture notes, administrative correspondence, evaluations, and curricular materials from the archives course.
  - Archives Lectures
    - Administration (Box 19)
    - Arrangement (Box 19)
    - Course Outline 727 (Box 19)
    - Demo Materials (Box 19)
    - Early Archives Course Lectures 1991 (Box 19)
    - Immigration History and Research Conference (Box 19)
    - Institutes (at Case Western) (Box 19)
    - Introduction (Box 19)
    - Jobs (Box 19)
    - Multicultural History Society of Ontario Finnish Forum (Box 19)
    - Misc. Topics (Box 19)
    - Ohio Historical Society (Box 19)
    - Planning and Funding New Buildings (Box 19)
    - Problems with Administration (Box 19)
    - Seminar Material (Box 19)
  - History Lectures
    - History Lectures: Michigan History (Box 20)
    - History 184: Michigan Geography Indians (Box 20)
    - History 184: Michigan Under French and British (Box 20)
    - History 184: Michigan as US Territory (Box 20)
    - History 184: General Notes (Box 20)
    - History 184, 577, 578: Nature of Course (Box 20)
    - History 184: Sources of Michigan History (Box 20)
    - History: Michigan Territory after the War of 1812 (Box 20)
    - History 184: Politics 1837-1860 (Box 20)
    - History 184: Educational, Social, Cultural Developments (Box 20)
    - History 184: Lumbering (Box 20)
    - History 184: Mining: Copper, Iron (Box 20)
    - History 184: Building Soo Canal (Box 20)
    - History 184: Anti-Slavery (Box 20)
    - History 184: Civil War (Box 20)
    - History 184: The Farm Problem 1865-1900 (Box 20)
    - History 184: Politics 1866-1896 (Box 20)
    - History 184: Immigration Population (Box 20)
    - History 184: Labor (Box 20)
    - History 184: Pingree -- Progressive Movement (Box 20)
    - History 184: Osborn -- Progressive Movement (Box 20)
    - History 184: WWI Politics 1920s 1918-30 (Box 20)
    - History 184: Urbanization, Automobile (Box 20)
    - History 184: New Deal (Box 20)
    - History 184: Williams Admin (Box 20)
    - History 577: British Regime (Box 20)
    - History 577: General Notes, Outline (Box 20)
    - History 577: Exam (Box 20)
    - History 578: Official Reading Lists (Box 20)
    - History 578: History of Michigan Outlines and Notes (Box 20)
    - History 578: Outlines and Research Paper Instructions (Box 20)
    - History 578: Research Paper Instructions (Box 20)
    - History 578: Sample Book Reports (Box 20)
    - History 578: Reading Lists (Box 20)
    - History 578: Examinations (Box 20)
    - History 578: Examination Duplicates (Box 20)
    - History 578: Recent Newspaper Clippings (Box 20)
    - History 578: Evaluations (Box 20)
    - History 578: Evaluations 1962 (Box 20)
    - History 578: Constitutions 1835 50, 1908, 1963 (Box 20)
    - History: Romney Biography (Box 20)
    - US History Topics and Course Outlines (Box 20)
    - History: Finding Aid Reading Course (Box 20)
    - History Thesis and Dissertation Committee Correspondence (Box 20)
    - Archives PhD candidate's oral and written exam (Box 20)
  - UCLA
    - Archives Course, Ham Richardson (Box 20)
    - Administrative Correspondence (Box 20)
    - Exams and Schedules (Box 20)
    - Student Evaluations (Box 20)
  - Publications, Research Notes and Drafts
    - Printed Publications 1955-1968 (Box 21)
    - Printed Publications 1970-1979 (Box 21)
    - Printed Publications 1980-1989 (Box 21)
    - Chase Osborne
      - Osborn Research Notes (Box 21)
      - Correspondence: Mrs. Chase Osborn (Box 21)
      - Thesis Correspondence (not with Mrs. Osborn) (Box 21)
      - Jane Warner's Notes on Chase Osborn (Box 21)
      - Michigan Academy and Chase Osborn (Box 21)
    - Dental History Notes (Box 21)
    - Dimensions of Progressivism: Drafts (Box 21)
    - Drafts (Box 21)
    - Final Master-Manual on Administration 1980 (Box 21)
    - Ford Papers: History (Box 21)
    - The Free Pass: Draft and Notes for (Box 21)
    - Frost, Robert-Bibliography and Notes (Box 21)
    - Henry Billings Brown and the "Separate but Equal" Decision (Box 21)
    - International Archival Adventures (1.21) (Box 21)
    - Local History Bibliography and Projects (Box 21)
    - Possible Articles (Box 21)
    - Prolog Article Drafts (Box 21)
  - Diary of a Dream
    - Diary of a Dream Notes, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Diary of a Dream Early Draft, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Diary of a Dream Pre-Publication (Box 21)
    - Diary of a Dream Post-Publication (Box 21)
- Professional Activities
  The Professional Activities series (10 linear feet) documents Warner's professional participation with groups outside his main appointments at the Michigan Historical Collection, the Archives of the US, and as Dean at Michigan. Included are correspondence and administrative items from the Citizens Ambassador Program (for which he lead a team to China in 1986), the Foundation of the National Archives, the Gerald R. Ford Foundation, International Council of Archives, National Historical Publications and Records Commission, Society of American Archivists, and other professional boards and committees. The series also contains articles, clippings and correspondence relating to Presidential libraries, including one file for each existing Presidential Library and information on the Hiss Deposition of 1998 for which Warner submitted an affidavit. Also of note is a series of SAA questionnaires filled out by universities across the country that offered archives courses. Warner's Recommendation letters from this period are restricted until 2070.
  - General: Professional Meetings, Committees, and Reports
    - America Historical Association (AHA): National Coordination Committee (Box 22)
    - Charles Babbage Institute Site Selection Committee (Box 22)
    - Clarke Historical Libraries Meetings (Box 22)
    - Conservation Division (Box 22)
    - Foundation for the National Archives, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Historical Markers (Box 22)
    - Joint Appointment Task Force Committee, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Museum Practice Program (Box 22)
    - Muskingum College (Box 22)
    - National Historical Publications and Records Commission (Box 22)
    - Presbyterian Historical Society Report 2001 (Box 22)
    - Rotary Club of Ann Arbor (Box 22)
    - Solicitation of Gifts for the President's House (Box 22)
    - University of Michigan Library Director Search Committee, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Washtenaw Historical Society Director Search Committee (Box 22)
    - Youth for Understanding Board (Box 22)
  - Citizens Ambassador Program
    - Citizen Ambassador Program, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - China (Box 22)
    - Russia (Box 22)
  - Foundation of the National Archives 1992-2003 (Box 23)
  - Foundation of the National Archives 2004-2005 (Box 24)
  - NARA clippings and lectures, 4 folders (Box 24)
  - General Accounting Office (GAO) Research and Education Panel (REAP) 1986-2000 (Box 24)
  - General Accounting Office (GAO) History Advisory Program Committee 1985-1996 (Box 24)
  - Gerald R. Ford Foundation
    - Annual Meetings 1986-2006 (Box 25)
    - Events (Box 25)
    - Correspondence (Box 25)
    - Library Liaison Committee 11/09/1988 (Box 25)
    - Ford Library Advisory Committee (Box 25)
    - Ford Museum (Box 25)
  - Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy (Box 25)
  - International Council on Archives (ICA)
    - Commission on Archival Development (CAD) (Box 26)
    - Executive Committee 1985, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Executive Committee 1986, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Executive Committee 1987, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - International Roundtable 1982 Kuala Lumpur (Box 26)
    - International Roundtable 1986 Helsinki (Box 26)
    - International Roundtable 1987 Italy (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous Information (Box 26)
    - NARS International Updates (Box 26)
    - Second European Council, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Training and Education Committee, 2 folders (Box 26)
  - National Academy of Public Administration (NAPA)
    - Electronic Archives Panel May 1988 (Box 27)
    - Electronic Archives Panel July 1988 (Box 27)
    - Electronic Archives Panel September 1988, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Electronic Archives Final Draft (Box 27)
  - National Library of Education Task Force
    - Agenda and Minutes (Box 27)
    - Briefing Book (Box 27)
    - Correspondence (Box 27)
    - Draft Reports (Box 27)
    - Educational Resource Information Center (ERIC) (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 27)
  - Presidential Libraries
    - Presidential Libraries: Statements and Correspondence (Box 28)
    - Presidential Libraries: Articles and Clippings (Box 28)
    - Bush Library (Box 28)
    - Carter Presidential Center (Box 28)
    - Clinton Library (Box 28)
    - Eisenhower Library (Box 28)
    - Ford Library (Box 28)
    - Hoover Library (Box 28)
    - Johnson Library (Box 28)
    - Kennedy Library (Box 28)
    - Nixon Library (Box 28)
    - Reagan Library (Box 28)
    - Roosevelt Library (Box 28)
    - Truman Library (Box 28)
    - Hiss Deposition 1998 (Box 28)
    - Princeton Conference on Presidential Libraries (Box 28)
  - Society of American Archivists (SAA)
    - International Archival Affairs (Box 29)
    - Professional Standards Committee (Box 29)
    - Education and Training Committee 1970-1973 (Box 29)
    - Education and Training Committee 1976 (Box 29)
    - Committees 1977-1979 (Box 29)
    - AHA/OAH/SAA (general) (Box 29)
    - AHA/OAH/SAA Joint Committee 1973-1975 (Box 29)
    - AHA/OAH/SAA Joint Committee 1977 (Box 29)
    - OAH/Spring Council Meeting 1977 Atlanta (Box 29)
    - SAA Conference 1974 (Box 29)
    - SAA Conference 1975 (Box 29)
    - SAA Conference 1976 (Box 29)
    - SAA Conference 1977, 3 folders (Box 29)
    - SAA Conference 1978 (Box 29)
    - SAA Conference 1979-1980 (Box 29)
    - SAA Correspondence and Activities
      - 1964-1965 (Box 30)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 30)
      - 1972 (Box 30)
      - 1973 (Box 30)
      - 1974 (Box 30)
      - 1975 (Box 30)
      - 1976 (Box 30)
    - SAA Education and Training Questionnaire and materials for University Archival Programs
      - American University (Box 30)
      - UCLA (Box 30)
      - Case Western University (Box 30)
      - Columbia University (Box 30)
      - Denver College (Box 30)
      - University of Illinois, Urbane, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - University of Maryland (Box 30)
      - University of Michigan, Dearborn (Box 30)
      - McGill University (Box 30)
      - University of New Brunswick (Box 30)
      - North Caroline State University (Box 30)
      - Ohio Historical Society (Box 30)
      - Sacramento State College (Box 30)
      - Washington University (Box 30)
      - University of Wisconsin (Box 30)
    - SAA Projects, Positions, and Committees
      - Conference 1977 Presentation Binder (Box 31)
      - Archives Library Relationships (Box 31)
      - Automated Records and Techniques (Box 31)
      - Awards (Box 31)
      - Building and Technical Equipment (Box 31)
      - Collecting Personal Papers and Manuscripts (Box 31)
      - College and University Archives (Box 31)
      - Constitution Revision Committee (Box 31)
      - Council Minutes and Treasury Reports (Box 31)
      - Education and Professional Development (Box 31)
      - Ethnic Archives (Box 31)
      - Finding Aids (Box 31)
      - New Harmony Conference 1976 Indiana (Box 31)
      - Joint ALA/SAA on Archives & Library Relationships (Box 31)
      - Labor Archives (Box 31)
      - Micrographics Committee (Box 31)
      - Nomination Committee (Box 31)
      - Oral History (Box 31)
      - Preservation Methods (Box 31)
      - Program 77 (Box 31)
      - Records Management (Box 31)
      - Reference and Access Policies (Box 31)
      - Regional Archival Activity (Box 31)
      - Religious Activities (Box 31)
      - State and Local Records (Box 31)
      - Status of Women (Box 31)
      - Terminology and Uniform Statistics (Box 31)
      - Urban Archives (Box 31)
      - Vice President, 2 folders (Box 31)
- Speeches
  The Speeches series (1 linear foot) maintains Warner's chronological arrangement of his speeches given between 1980 and 1999 and has nine additional folders of notes and speeches for other various events.
  - 1980-1999, 18 folders (Box 32)
  - Albion College Speech 08/03/1998 (Box 32)
  - Angel in China (Box 32)
  - Robert Frost 2000 (Box 32)